{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "In Bengal, the East India Company's headquarters were located at",
            "optionA": "  Fort St George ",
            "optionB": "  Fort william ",
            "optionC": "  Fort St David ",
            "optionD": "  Shantiniketan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe headquarters of East India Company were located at Fort William in Bengal. Fort William is a fort built in Calcutta (presently Kolkata) on the eastern banks of the River Hooghly, the major distributary of the River Ganges, during the early years of the Bengal Presidency of British India. It was named after King William III of England. In front of the Fort is the Maidan, which used to be a part of the Fort and is the largest urban park in Calcutta. ",
            "keyString": "598566s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who established the Sadr-Di-wani-Adalat during the British East India Company's rule?",
            "optionA": "  Wellesley ",
            "optionB": "  Warren Hastings ",
            "optionC": "  Dalhousie ",
            "optionD": "  Cornwallis ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSadr-Di-wani-Adalat during Mughal and British rule in India was a High Court of Civil and Revenue matters.The \u1e62adr D\u012bw\u0101n\u012b \u02bfAd\u0101lat was the Supreme Court of Revenue in British India established at Calcutta by Warren Hastings in 1772. It was reformed in 1780 and again in 1793 by the British Parliament. ",
            "keyString": "598599s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1612 __________established a trading post in Gujarat",
            "optionA": "  British ",
            "optionB": "  French ",
            "optionC": "  Spain ",
            "optionD": "  Dutch ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBritish established a trading post in 1612 at Gujarat. ",
            "keyString": "598613s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After the commencement of the government of India Act-1858, what name was to British Governor-General of India?",
            "optionA": "  Governor-General of India ",
            "optionB": "  Governor of the state ",
            "optionC": "  Viceroy of the state ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter the commencement of the government of India Act-1858, Viceroy of the state was to British Governor-General of India. ",
            "keyString": "598625s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Author of Poverty and Un-British Rule in India is__________",
            "optionA": "  Romila Thapar ",
            "optionB": "  Irfan Habib ",
            "optionC": "  S.",
            "optionD": "Ghosh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNaoroji Dadabhai Is the author of books such as Poverty and Un-British Rule In India. ",
            "keyString": "598636s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following events made the English East India Company the legitimate masters of the Bengal Suba?",
            "optionA": "  Battle of Buxar, 1764 ",
            "optionB": "  Battle of Plassey, 1757 ",
            "optionC": "  Farrukh Siyar's Farman, 1717 ",
            "optionD": "  Ibrahim Khan's Farman, 1690 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEnglish East India Company became the legitimate masters of Bengal Suba after battle of Buxar which was held on 22 Oct, 1764 between East lndia company led by Hector Munro and Mir Qasim (Nawab of Bengal), Mughal emperor Shah Alam, Nawab of Avadh Shira-jud-daula. ",
            "keyString": "645578s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Government of India Act introduced the diarchy system in the provinces of India?",
            "optionA": "  Government of India Act, 1909 ",
            "optionB": "  Government of India Act, 1919 ",
            "optionC": "  Government of India Act, 1935 ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDyarchy, also spelled diarchy, system of double government introduced by the Government of India Act (1919) for the provinces of British India. Dyarchy was introduced as a constitutional reform by Edwin Samuel Montagu (secretary of state for India, 1917\u201322) and Lord Chelmsford (viceroy of India, 1916\u201321). ",
            "keyString": "645612s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nana Sahib the adopted son of Peshwa Baji Rao II had become a great enemy of the British because",
            "optionA": "  The Queen had humiliated him ",
            "optionB": "  He had lost his title ",
            "optionC": "  The British had stopped his pension ",
            "optionD": "  His estate had been snatched from him ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNana Saheb was the adopted son of Peshwa Baji Rao II. His annual pension was stopped because the British refused to recognize him as the legitimate heir to the throne as he was adopted. ",
            "keyString": "645628s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "British Prime Minister Attlee made the historic announcement of the end of British rule in India (and transfer of power to responsible Indian hands by a date not later than June1948) on",
            "optionA": "  May 16, 1946 ",
            "optionB": "  February 20, 1947 ",
            "optionC": "  March 10, 1946 ",
            "optionD": "  December 31, 1946 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Prime Minister of the United Kingdom announced on 20 February 1947 that: the British Government would grant full self-government to British India by 30 June 1948 at the latest, The future of the Princely States would be decided after the date of final transfer is decided. ",
            "keyString": "645642s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Viceroy who wanted to train Indian in the art of selfgovernment was",
            "optionA": "  Mountbatten ",
            "optionB": "  Ripon ",
            "optionC": "  Northbrook ",
            "optionD": "  Curzon ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRipon was a true democrat. He took some steps towards liberalizing the administration in India. His aim was to give popular and political education to the Indians. He formulated the local self government and laid the foundations of representative institutions in India. ",
            "keyString": "645654s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When the East India Company was formed, the Mughal emperor in India was",
            "optionA": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionB": "  Humayun ",
            "optionC": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "optionD": "  Akbar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe East India Company was incorporated by royal charter on December 31, 1600. It was an English company formed for the exploitation of trade with East and Southeast Asia and India during the reign of Mughal Emperor Akbar (1556-1605). ",
            "keyString": "697441s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The British India Society was formed in __________",
            "optionA": "  1832 ",
            "optionB": "  1833 ",
            "optionC": "  1839 ",
            "optionD": "  1874 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe British India Society (1839): Founded in London with the efforts of William Adam, one of the friends of Raja Ram Mohan Roy. He along with George Thompson, William Ednis, and Major General Briggs organised meetings and enlightened people about the miserable conditions in India. ",
            "keyString": "697480s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When the Congress Ministries were formed in the provinces in June 1937, the Viceroy of India was",
            "optionA": "  Lord Willingdon ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Irwin ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Linlithgow ",
            "optionD": "  Viscount Wavell ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe All-India Muslim League failed to form the government in any province. The Congress ministries resigned in October and November 1939, in protest against Viceroy Lord Linlithgow's action of declaring India to be a belligerent in the Second World War without consulting the Indian people. ",
            "keyString": "697492s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Mysore War Fought between the British and Hyder Ali in 1767- 1769 A.D., came to an end by the",
            "optionA": "  Treaty of Pondicherry ",
            "optionB": "  Treaty of Madras ",
            "optionC": "  Treaty of Mysore ",
            "optionD": "  Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1767 Mysore was a powerful state under Hyder Ali. In 1769, the first Anglo-Mysore war was fought in which Haider Ali defeated the British and Treaty of Madras was signed between them. Haider Ali occupied almost the whole of Carnatic. ",
            "keyString": "697502s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The British Government intervened in the affairs of the Company and passed an Act in 1773 A.D., known as the",
            "optionA": "  Regulating Act ",
            "optionB": "  Pitt's India Act ",
            "optionC": "  Charter Act ",
            "optionD": "  Company Act ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRegulating Act, (1773), legislation passed by the British Parliament for the regulation of the British East India Company's Indian territories, mainly in Bengal. The act was amended and the government of India was recast by Prime Minister William Pitt's India Act of 1784. ",
            "keyString": "697513s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________ started an all-India campaign for restoring the entrance age of 21 and for simultaneous ICS examination in India",
            "optionA": "  Gokahale ",
            "optionB": "  S. N. Banerjee ",
            "optionC": "  Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  William Logan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tS.N. Banerjee started an all-India campaign for restoring the entrance age of 21 and for simultaneous ICS examination in India. ",
            "keyString": "746285s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following Viceroys became a victim of one of the convicts during his visit to the Andamans?",
            "optionA": "  Curzon ",
            "optionB": "  Mayo ",
            "optionC": "  Ripon ",
            "optionD": "  Lytton ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Mayo was stabbed when he was in Andamans. He was first and last Viceory murdered in India.",
            "keyString": "746376s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India was granted freedom during the British Prime Minister",
            "optionA": "  Clement Attlee ",
            "optionB": "  Winston Churchill ",
            "optionC": "  Ramsay Mac Donald ",
            "optionD": "  William Pitt ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Independence Act 1947 passed on 1st August 1947 by the British Parliament in reign of Prime minister Clement Attlee (Labour party). On 14 August 1947 India divided into two dominion states Pakistan (14th August) and India (15th August). ",
            "keyString": "746404s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By the Charter Act of 1813 the Indian trade except in __________ was thrown open to all British subjects",
            "optionA": "  Tea ",
            "optionB": "  Spices ",
            "optionC": "  Coffee ",
            "optionD": "  Cotton ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCharter act of 1813 ended the monopoly of the East India Company in India, however the company's monopoly in trade with china and trade in tea with India was kept intact. Thus, trade with India for all commodities except Tea was thrown open to all British subjects. ",
            "keyString": "746429s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Before the Regulating Act was passed in 1773, there was __________ at home to administer the East India Company",
            "optionA": "  A Committee of 24 ",
            "optionB": "  A Secretary ",
            "optionC": "  A Council of Lords ",
            "optionD": "  A Board of Revenue ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBefore the Regulating Act was passed in 1773, there was A Committee of 24 at home to, administer the East India Company. ",
            "keyString": "746449s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The State Jhansi was made a part of the British Empire in India through",
            "optionA": "  Doctrine of Lapse ",
            "optionB": "  Policy of Subsidiaty Alliance ",
            "optionC": "  War against Rani Lakshmi Bai ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Dalhousie introduced the Doctrine of Lapse i.e any princely state under the direct influence of East India Company, as a vassal state under the British SubsidiarySystem wouldautomatically be annexed if the ruler was either\"manifestly in competent or died without a male heir.The series of state annexed - Satara, Jaipur, Sambhal pur, Jhansi (1854). ",
            "keyString": "794773s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first strategically placed factory that the Britishers had fortified was at",
            "optionA": "  Surat ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay ",
            "optionC": "  Masulipatnam ",
            "optionD": "  Madras ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEnglishmen\u2019s easy success in trade and in establishing independent and fortified settlements at Madras and at Bombay, and the preoccupation of Aurangzeb with the anti-Maratha campaigns led the English to abandon the role of humble petitioners. ",
            "keyString": "794893s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who convinced the British in 1829 to outlaw Sati?",
            "optionA": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionB": "  Swami Dayananda Saraswati ",
            "optionC": "  Lokmanya Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Ram Mohan Roy convinced the British in 1829 to outlaw Sati. ",
            "keyString": "794932s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Vernacular Press Act was passed in __________",
            "optionA": "  1878 ",
            "optionB": "  1881 ",
            "optionC": "  1888 ",
            "optionD": "  1898 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe act was proposed by Lord Lytton, then Viceroy of India, and was unanimously passed by the Viceroy's Council on 14 March 1878. ",
            "keyString": "794960s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi gave up the title of Kaiser-i-Hind and returned all the war medals which were awarded to him by the British for his war services (during the First World War)",
            "optionA": "  in protest against the Jallianwala Bagh tragedy ",
            "optionB": "  during the Non-Cooperation Movement ",
            "optionC": "  in support of the Khilafat demand when the Central Khilafat Committee organised a general all-India hartal on August 1, 1920 ",
            "optionD": "  during the Champaran Satyagraha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi gave up the title of Kaiser-i-Hind and returned all the war medals which were awarded to him by the British for his war services (during the First World War) in support of the Khilafat demand when the Central Khilafat Committee organised a general all-India hartal on August 1, 1920. ",
            "keyString": "794984s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the 18th Century the Royal prerogative in the affairs of the East India Company was controlled by",
            "optionA": "  The Viceroy's Council ",
            "optionB": "  The Indian Legislature ",
            "optionC": "  The Parliament in England ",
            "optionD": "  The Secretary of State ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the 18th Century the Royal prerogative in the affairs of the East India Company was controlled byThe Parliament in England. ",
            "keyString": "844613s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In March 1942, British Prime Minister Winston Churchill appointed the Cripps Mission to resolve Indian political crisis because",
            "optionA": "  he was under pressure from the US President Roosevelt ",
            "optionB": "  of the gravity of the Japanese war menace on India's borders ",
            "optionC": "  both A and B above ",
            "optionD": "  of INA's initial success on India's eastern borders ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn March 1942, British Prime Minister Winston Churchill appointed the Cripps Mission to resolve Indian political crisis because he was under pressure from the US President Roosevelt and of the gravity of the Japanese war menace on India's borders. ",
            "keyString": "844832s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As the unrest continued unabatedly, the Madras government appointed . . . . . . the collector of Malabar as special commissioner to enquire into the causes of the uprisings and recommend remedial measures.",
            "optionA": "  Connolly ",
            "optionB": "  William Logan ",
            "optionC": "  S. N. Banerjee ",
            "optionD": "  Gokahale ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWilliam Logan (1841\u20131914) was a Scottish officer of the Madras Civil Service under the British Government. Before his appointment as Collector of Malabar, he had served in the area for about twenty years in the capacity of Magistrate and Judge. He was conversant in Malayalam, Tamil and Telugu. ",
            "keyString": "844891s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following British Prime Minister headed the First Round Table Conference in London?",
            "optionA": "  Churchill ",
            "optionB": "  Ramsay McDonald ",
            "optionC": "  Chamberlain ",
            "optionD": "  Disraeli ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Round Table Conference officially inaugurated by George V on November 12, 1930 in Royal Gallery House of Lords at London and chaired by the British Prime Minister, Ramsay MacDonald. The three British political parties were represented by sixteen delegates. ",
            "keyString": "844916s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1661 the company obtained __________ from Charles II",
            "optionA": "  Bombay ",
            "optionB": "  Madras ",
            "optionC": "  Kannur ",
            "optionD": "  Calcutta ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 11 May 1661, the marriage treaty of Charles II of England and Catherine of Braganza, daughter of King John IV of Portugal, placed Bombay in the possession of the British Empire, as part of Catherine's dowry to Charles. ",
            "keyString": "844942s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Vernacular Press Act was repealed by __________",
            "optionA": "  Lord Ripon ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Lytton ",
            "optionC": "  Lord William Bentic ",
            "optionD": "  Gladstone ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVernacular Press Act, in British India, law enacted in 1878 to curtail the freedom of the Indian-language (i.e., non-English) press. The law was repealed in 1881 by Lytton's successor as viceroy, Lord Ripon (governed 1880-84). ",
            "keyString": "899943s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which Charter Act, the East India Company's monopoly of trade with China come to an end?",
            "optionA": "  Charter Act of 1793 ",
            "optionB": "  Charter Act of 1813 ",
            "optionC": "  Charter Act of 1833 ",
            "optionD": "  Charter Act of 1853 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCharter Acts of 1813 was an Act of the Parliament of the United Kingdom which renewed the charter issued to the British East India Company, and continued the Company's rule in India. However, the Company's commercial monopoly was ended, except for the tea trade and the trade with China. The Charter Act of 1833 ended the monopoly in trade with China and the monopoly to trade in tea in India.",
            "keyString": "899975s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not among the regions where the Britishers had first set up trading posts?",
            "optionA": "  Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Goa ",
            "optionC": "  Coromandel Coast ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGoa is not among the regions where the Britishers had first set up trading posts. ",
            "keyString": "899990s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who propounded the theory of 'Economic Drain of India' during British imperialism?",
            "optionA": "  W. ",
            "optionB": " Bannerji ",
            "optionC": "  Dadabhai Naroji ",
            "optionD": "  Gopalkrishna Gokhale ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDadabhai Naoroji's work focused on the drain of wealth from India to England during colonial rule of British in India. One of the reasons that the Drain theory is attributed to Naoroji is his decision to estimate the net national profit of India, and by extension, the effect that colonisation has on the country. ",
            "keyString": "900002s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following who fought against British in 1857 Revolt?\nI. Kunwar Singh\nII. Tantia Tope\nIII. Nana Saheb\nIV. Maulavi Ahmaduallah",
            "optionA": "  All of the above ",
            "optionB": "  I, III and IV ",
            "optionC": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionD": "  II, III and IV ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of these four leaders fought against British in 1857 Revolt -Kunwar Singh- Bihar, Tanitia Tope- Gwalior, Nana Saheb- Kanpur, Maulavi Ahmaduallah- Faizabad. ",
            "keyString": "900014s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Government of India Act/Charter Act generated the post of Governor-General of India?",
            "optionA": "  Government of India Act-1858 ",
            "optionB": "  Charter Act-1833 ",
            "optionC": "  Charter Act-1853 ",
            "optionD": "  Charter Act-1813 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGovernor-General of Bengal was made Governor-General of India through the Charter Act of 1833. Under this provision Lord William Bentinck became the first Governor-General of India. It deprived the Governors of Bombay and Madras of their legislative powers. For the first time, the Governor-General's Government was known as the 'Government of India' and his council as the 'India Council' in 1858. ",
            "keyString": "945679s43m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1831 Bentinck signed a treaty with Ranjit Singh to protect the British territories from",
            "optionA": "  Russian menace ",
            "optionB": "  Pindari menace ",
            "optionC": "  Rohelas ",
            "optionD": "  Attack by Burmese ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1831 Bentinck signed a treaty with Ranjit Singh to protect the British territories from Russian menace. ",
            "keyString": "27034s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As a result of the partition of Bengal announced by Lord Curzon in 1905, Bengal was partitioned into two provinces of",
            "optionA": "  East Bengal and West Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Bengal and Eastern Bengal & Assam ",
            "optionC": "  Bengal and Assam ",
            "optionD": "  Bengal and Odisha and East Bengal and Assam ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs a result of the partition of Bengal announced by Lord Curzon in 1905, Bengal was partitioned into two provinces of Bengal and Eastern Bengal & Assam. ",
            "keyString": "27070s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Regulating Act was in the year of__________",
            "optionA": "  1573 ",
            "optionB": "  1673 ",
            "optionC": "  1773 ",
            "optionD": "  1873 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRegulating Act, (1773), legislation passed by the British Parliament for the regulation of the British East India Company's Indian territories, mainly in Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "27088s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Governor General of India who initiated the introduction of English in India was",
            "optionA": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Macaulay ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Bentinck ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Hastings ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn India Lord Macaulay (Thomas Balington Macaulay) is fully credited with the official introduction of English education though the necessary order on the subject were given by Lord William Bentinck the governor general of India on 7th March 1835. ",
            "keyString": "27104s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who made remarkable contribution to the development of Local government?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Ripon ",
            "optionB": "  Gladstone ",
            "optionC": "  W.W Hunter ",
            "optionD": "  Hastings ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Ripon made remarkable contribution to the development of local government. In 1882, he abandoned the existing system of local government by the officially nominated people. ",
            "keyString": "27118s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lord Mountbatten had replaced Lord __________ as the viceroy of India in 1947",
            "optionA": "  Wavell ",
            "optionB": "  Lytton ",
            "optionC": "  Linlithgow ",
            "optionD": "  Cornwallis ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Mountbatten had replaced Lord Wavell as the viceroy of India in 1947. ",
            "keyString": "83118s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The First Opium War started__________",
            "optionA": "  1729 ",
            "optionB": "  1736 ",
            "optionC": "  1839 ",
            "optionD": "  1939 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe First Opium War, fought over opium trade, financial reparations, and diplomatic status, began in 1839 and was concluded by the Treaty of Nanking (Nanjing) in 1842. ",
            "keyString": "83151s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following act led to the introduction of dual system of government in India?",
            "optionA": "  Pitt's India Act, AD 1784 ",
            "optionB": "  The Regulating Act, AD 1773 ",
            "optionC": "  Charter Act, 1793 AD ",
            "optionD": "  Charter Act, 1813 AD ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPitt's India Act 1784 or the East India Company Act 1784 was passed in the British Parliament to rectify the defects of the Regulating Act 1773. It resulted in dual control or joint government in India by Crown in Great Britain and the British East India Company, with crown having ultimate authority. ",
            "keyString": "83165s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the motive of Lord Wellesley to introduced the system of Subsidiary Alliance?",
            "optionA": "  Improve the administration of the Indian States ",
            "optionB": "  Prevent disloyalty towards the British ",
            "optionC": "  Tone up the British Indian administration ",
            "optionD": "  Prevent the French influence in the Indian States ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWellesley\u2019s aims were expansionism and imperialism. He wan\u00adted to expand the British dominions in India to such an extent that it should become the sovereign power in India. His expansionist mind would not remain content with British remaining one of the powers in India, as such he set himself to the task of converting India into an empire of Britain. Another aim, which was ancillary to his main objective, was removal of French influence from India and to make possibility of French territorial expansion of India impossible. ",
            "keyString": "83177s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Indian to be elected to the British Parliament?",
            "optionA": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionB": "  GopalaKrishna Gokhale ",
            "optionC": "  Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "optionD": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDadabhai Naroji was the first Anglo Indian to elect the British Parliament. He also known as Grand Old Man of India. He introduced, drain of wealth theory. ",
            "keyString": "83189s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first interim government during the British rule in India was formed in",
            "optionA": "  September, 1945 ",
            "optionB": "  November, 1945 ",
            "optionC": "  September, 1946 ",
            "optionD": "  January, 1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 2nd September 1946 the Interim Government of India was formed. This temporary government was formed from the Constituent Assembly of India (which was then newly elected). This government was entrusted the task of helping the transition of India and Pakistan from British rule to Independence as two separate nations. ",
            "keyString": "144783s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The English rounded Calcutta after obtaining the zamindari of three villages, viz Sutanuti, Kalikata and Govindpur, from the Mughal Viceroy of Bengal in 1698. The nucleus of the British settlement in Calcutta was",
            "optionA": "  San Thome ",
            "optionB": "  Victoria Memeorial ",
            "optionC": "  Fort William ",
            "optionD": "  Howrah Port ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tthe english rounded calcutta after obtaining the zamindari of three villages, viz sutanuti, kalikata and govindpur, from the mughal viceroy of bengal in 1698. The nucleus of the british settlement in calcutta was Fort William. ",
            "keyString": "144925s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The inauguration of the Ganapati and Shivaji Festivals was done by",
            "optionA": "  1721 ",
            "optionB": "  1821 ",
            "optionC": "  1895 ",
            "optionD": "  1921 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe inauguration of the Ganapati and Shivaji Festivals was done by 1895. ",
            "keyString": "144974s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________, a judge of the Supreme Court founded the Asiatic society of Bengal in 1784 A.D.",
            "optionA": "  Sir William Jones ",
            "optionB": "  Warren Hastings ",
            "optionC": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Macaulay ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Asiatic Society was founded by civil servant Sir William Jones on 15 January 1784 in a meeting presided over by Sir William Jones, Justice of the Supreme Court of Judicature at Fort William at the Fort William in Calcutta, then capital of the British Raj, to enhance and further the cause of Oriental research. ",
            "keyString": "145011s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Ilbert Bill introduced In Lord Ripon's reign is significant because",
            "optionA": "  it limited the Britishers political authority ",
            "optionB": "  it put restrictions on the vernacular press ",
            "optionC": "  it debarred Indians from entering the civil services ",
            "optionD": "  it removed racial discrimination from the judicial services ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe introduction of the bill led to intense opposition in Britain and from British settlers in India that ultimately played on racial tension before it was enacted in 1884 in a severely compromised state. The bitter controversy deepened antagonism between the British and Indians and was a prelude to the formation of the Indian National Congress in the next two years. There was also a strong protest among Europeans. ",
            "keyString": "145042s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the supreme body in the Britain at the time of commencement of the Government of India Act- 1858?",
            "optionA": "  Queen Victoria ",
            "optionB": "  The British Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  Government of Britan ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe British Parliament was the supreme body in the Britain at the time of commencement of the Government of India Act- 1858. ",
            "keyString": "190444s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not correct about Montegu- Chelmsford's Reform & Government of India Act, 1919?",
            "optionA": "  It changed the administrative system in India ",
            "optionB": "  In this Act the central legislative council was replaced by two houses-the imperial legislative assembly and the council of state ",
            "optionC": "  Education and public health were placed under charge of ministers responsible to the legislature ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above are incorrect ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Montagu\u2013Chelmsford Reforms or more briefly known as Mont-Ford Reforms were reforms introduced by the colonial government in British India to introduce self-governing institutions gradually to India. The reforms take their name from Edwin Samuel Montagu, the Secretary of State for India during the latter parts of World War I and Lord Chelmsford, Viceroy of India between 1916 and 1921. The reforms were outlined in the Montagu-Chelmsford Report prepared in 1918 and formed the basis of the Government of India Act 1919. ",
            "keyString": "190477s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not the part of Government of India Act, 1935",
            "optionA": "  This act provided for setting up of the federation of India comprising British Indian provinces ",
            "optionB": "  Diarchy in the provinces was replaced by provincial autonomy ",
            "optionC": "  The post of Indian council of secretary of state for India made permanent ",
            "optionD": "  The diarchy was introduced at the centre ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Secretary of state was Lord Stanley, who prior to 2 August 1858, served as President of the Board of Control. The Secretary of State was now the political head of the India. ",
            "keyString": "190491s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not the provision of government of India act, 1935?",
            "optionA": "  This act ended the system of diarchy ",
            "optionB": "  The structure for \"Federation of India\" was established for both British India and some or all of the \"princely states\" ",
            "optionC": "  Burma became the part of India ",
            "optionD": "  The introduction of direct elections, thus increasing the franchise from seven million to thirty-five million people ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe British colony of Burma was part of the British run-state in India, the Empire of India, from 1824 to 1937. It is not the provision of government of India act, 1935. ",
            "keyString": "190509s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Warren Hastings was appointed as the Governor of __________ in 1772",
            "optionA": "  Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Madras ",
            "optionC": "  Bombay ",
            "optionD": "  Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWarren Hastings (6 December 1732 \u2013 22 August 1818), an English statesman, was the first Governor of the Presidency of Fort William (Bengal), the head of the Supreme Council of Bengal, and thereby the first de facto Governor-General of India from 1772 to 1785. ",
            "keyString": "190523s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Company lost all its administrative powers__________",
            "optionA": "  By the Government of India Act of 1658 ",
            "optionB": "  By the Government of India Act of 1758 ",
            "optionC": "  By the Government of India Act of 1858 ",
            "optionD": "  By the Government of India Act of 1958 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBritish Parliament brought the Government of India Act, 1858, which made the following changes: i. Transferred powers from the East India Company to the Crown. ii. A member of British Parliament was made secretary of state of India to exercise powers on behalf of the Crown and was responsible to the British Parliament. iii. The Governor General for India was provided with an Executive Council, whose decision he was empowered to override. ",
            "keyString": "283319s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The momentous decision to transfer the capital from Calcutta to Delhi, to annul the partition of Bengal and to abolish Indian indentured labour were taken during the Viceroyalty of Lord",
            "optionA": "  Hardinge ",
            "optionB": "  Minto ",
            "optionC": "  Chelmsford ",
            "optionD": "  Reading ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt that time, Lord Hardinge was the Governor General of the British held territories in India, and he was the one that shifted the capital of India from Calcutta to Delhi. ",
            "keyString": "283351s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Till the end of the 17th Century the growth of the executive and legislative powers of the East india Company depended on",
            "optionA": "  Governor ",
            "optionB": "  Governor-General ",
            "optionC": "  Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  Crown ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTill the end of the 17th Century the growth of the executive and legislative powers of the East India Company depended on Crown. ",
            "keyString": "283365s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In November 1781, Sir Eyre Coote defeated __________ at Porto Nova",
            "optionA": "  Hyder Ali ",
            "optionB": "  Marthanda Verma ",
            "optionC": "  British ",
            "optionD": "  Tipu Sultan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Porto Novo was fought on 1 July 1781 between forces of the Kingdom of Mysore and British East India Company in the place called Porto Novo (now known as Parangipettai) on the Indian subcontinent, during the Second Anglo-Mysore War. The British force, numbering more than 8,000 under the command of Sir Eyre Coote defeated a force estimated at 40,000 under the command of Hyder Ali. ",
            "keyString": "283378s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The English East Company achieved a major victory over the Portuguese in the Battle of __________ in 1612",
            "optionA": "  Buxar ",
            "optionB": "  Plassey ",
            "optionC": "  Swally ",
            "optionD": "  Trafalgar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe naval Battle of Swally, also known as Battle of Suvali, took place on 29\u201330 November 1612 off the coast of Suvali (anglicised to Swally) a village near the Surat city (now in Gujarat, India) and was a victory for four English East India Company galleons over four Portuguese galleons and 26 barks (rowing vessels with no armament). ",
            "keyString": "283389s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the Governor General of India during the Civil Disobedience Movement?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Chelmsford ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Reading ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Irwin ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Wavell ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Irwin was the Governor General and Viceroy of India (1926-1931). On April 3, 1926 Lord Irwin was appointed 30th Viceroy and Governor-General of India. This was the most tumultuous period for the politics of India. ",
            "keyString": "328093s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who tried to rediscover India's past?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Lytton ",
            "optionB": "  Max Muller ",
            "optionC": "  S. N. Banerjee ",
            "optionD": "  Gokahale ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMax Muller ",
            "keyString": "328127s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The process of the introduction of education in English had been initiated in India by Lord",
            "optionA": "  Curzon ",
            "optionB": "  Bentick ",
            "optionC": "  Hastings ",
            "optionD": "  Macaulay ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThomas Babington Macaulay was the secretary to the Board of control of India during the British rule. He was the secretary under Lord Grey from 1832 to 1833. He is known for his Minute on Indian Education which came out in February 1835. He wanted to teach English to the people of India and not Sanskrit or Persian. ",
            "keyString": "328141s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Select the correct chronological sequence of the following events?\nI. Appointment of the Simon Commission.\nII. Formation of the first Labour Government in Britain.\nIII. Submission of the Nehru report.\nIV. Inauguration of the First Round Table Conference",
            "optionA": "  II, I, III & IV ",
            "optionB": "  I, III, IV & II ",
            "optionC": "  I, II, IV & III ",
            "optionD": "  II, IV, I & III ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tI. Appointment of the Simon Commission - November 1927 II. Formation of the first Labour Government in Britain - January 1924 III. Submission of the Nehru report - August 1928 IV. Inauguration of the First Round Table Conference - November 1930 ",
            "keyString": "328153s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was meant by the secretary of State of India during the British?",
            "optionA": "  An official who worked as the Secretary to the\nViceroy of India ",
            "optionB": "  A Secretary level official appointed in each\nPresidency of India ",
            "optionC": "  A British minister given full control over the\nGovernment of India ",
            "optionD": "  A senior officer appointed the Viceroy to look\ninto his internal administration in India ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSecretary of State is also deemed as Political Head of India. The post was created in Charter Act of 1858. The first Secretary of state was Lord Stanley. ",
            "keyString": "328168s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Dadabhai Naoroji's book 'poverty and un British rule in India' published in __________ analysed the nature of the British rule in India",
            "optionA": "  1898 ",
            "optionB": "  1901 ",
            "optionC": "  1908 ",
            "optionD": "  1946 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNaoroji published Poverty and un-British Rule in India in 1901. It analysed the nature of the British rule in India. ",
            "keyString": "372050s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the British Governor- General shown great interest in the preservation of ancient monuments?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Ripon ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Lytton ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Irwin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe British Governor- General Lord Curzon shown great interest in the preservation of ancient monuments. ",
            "keyString": "372083s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When the East India Company was established India was ruled by",
            "optionA": "  A Mughal Emperor ",
            "optionB": "  A Gupta Emperor ",
            "optionC": "  A Mauryan Emperor ",
            "optionD": "  A Sunga Emperor ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen the East India Company was established India was ruled by a Mughal Emperor. ",
            "keyString": "372097s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following revolutionaries was executed by the British",
            "optionA": "  Jitin Das ",
            "optionB": "  Chandrashekhar Azad ",
            "optionC": "  Rajguru ",
            "optionD": "  Kalpana - Dutt ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShivaram Hari Rajguru (24 August 1908 \u2013 23 March 1931) was an Indian revolutionary from Maharashtra, known mainly for his involvement in the assassination of a British Raj police officer.",
            "keyString": "372109s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the Second World War the British forces were defeated at __________",
            "optionA": "  London ",
            "optionB": "  Dunkirk ",
            "optionC": "  Paris ",
            "optionD": "  Liverpool ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs part of the Battle of France on the Western Front, the Battle of Dunkirk was the defence and evacuation to Britain of British and other Allied forces in Europe from 26 May to 4 June 1940. After the Phoney War, the Battle of France began in earnest on 10 May 1940. ",
            "keyString": "372121s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The violent Mappilas stormed the bungalow of the District Magistrate . . . . . . and murdered him in 1855",
            "optionA": "  H.V. Connolly ",
            "optionB": "  William Logan ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Ripond ",
            "optionD": "  Gladstone ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt about 9 p.m. on the evening of 11 September 1855 Conolly was attacked and killed at the Collector's Residence at West Hill Bungalow, Calicut by a small group of Mappilas. Conolly was buried in what is now Conolly Park, near South Beach Road; the headstone of his tomb was moved to the premises of the C.S.I. St. Mary's English Church, Calicut in 1997. ",
            "keyString": "410813s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Treaty of Surat was in the year __________",
            "optionA": "  1475 ",
            "optionB": "  1575 ",
            "optionC": "  1675 ",
            "optionD": "  1775 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Treaty of Surat (6 March 1775) was a treaty by which Raghunathrao, one of the claimants to the throne of the Peshwa, agreed to cede Salsette and Bassein Fort to the English, in consideration of being himself restored to Poona. The military operations that followed are known as the First Anglo-Maratha War. ",
            "keyString": "410845s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): British excluded the Indian middle and upper classes from the high administrative and military posts.\nReason (R): Many of the traditional zamindars lost their zamindaris to the new class of urban-based absentee landlords",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R is true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R is true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMany of them lost their zamindaris to the new class of urban-based absentee landlords due to the introduction of the zamindari or the new class of urban-based absentee landlords due to the introduction of zamindari or the permanent settlement, and the strict manner of revenue collection by the British. ",
            "keyString": "410861s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1877 the entrance age to ICS was reduced from 21 to __________",
            "optionA": "  17 ",
            "optionB": "  18 ",
            "optionC": "  19 ",
            "optionD": "  20 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1877 the entrance age to ICS was reduced from 21 to 19. ",
            "keyString": "410875s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Charles Wood's Despatch__________",
            "optionA": "  1554  ",
            "optionB": "  1684 ",
            "optionC": "  1784 ",
            "optionD": "  1854 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSir Charles Wood, the President of the Board of Control, had an important effect on spreading English learning and female education in India. When in 1855 he sent a despatch to Lord Dalhousie, the then Governor-General of India.Wood suggested that primary colleges must adopt vernacular languages, high schools must adopt Anglo verncular language and on college level English medium for education. This is known as Wood's despatch. Vocational and women's education were not stressed upon. ",
            "keyString": "410887s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian naval mutiny against the British took place in the year",
            "optionA": "  1857 ",
            "optionB": "  1919 ",
            "optionC": "  1946 ",
            "optionD": "  1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Naval Ratings mutiny took place in 1946. Basically, it started as the sailors were dissatisfied with the food they were given. This snowballed into a mutiny against British rule. The mutiny started in Bombay Dock. ",
            "keyString": "449198s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The land was owned by temples known as __________",
            "optionA": "  Dewaswam ",
            "optionB": "  Brahmaswam ",
            "optionC": "  Cherikkal ",
            "optionD": "  Kanam ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Kerala, temples are managed by Devaswom Board,which comes under the government of Kerala. ",
            "keyString": "449233s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Dyer was __________ by the Government of Britain",
            "optionA": "  Sentenced for life ",
            "optionB": "  Sentenced to death ",
            "optionC": "  Rewarded with honour ",
            "optionD": "  Relieved of his service ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter the Punjab disturbances, O'Dyer was relieved of his office by the government of Britain. ",
            "keyString": "449249s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The capital of British India was transferred from Calcutta to Delhi in the year",
            "optionA": "  1911 ",
            "optionB": "  1912 ",
            "optionC": "  1920 ",
            "optionD": "  1925 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDelhi was officially announced as the capital of British Raj by the then-Emperor George V, on December 12, 1911. The capital was shifted from Calcutta as Delhi was the financial and political seat of many earlier empires and was located closer to the geographical center of India. ",
            "keyString": "449263s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The transfer of Government from the 'Company' to the 'Crown' was pronounced by Lord Canning (November 1, 1858) at",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionB": "  Delhi ",
            "optionC": "  Patna ",
            "optionD": "  Allahabad ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo declare the assumption of the Government of India by the crown a Durbar was held at Allahabad on November 1, 1858, by the Viceroy Lord Canning. Queen`s proclamation was read by Lord Canning. As per the proclamation, the administration of India came into the direct hands of British Government. ",
            "keyString": "449275s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The decisive battle of the third Carnatic War was waged between the French and the British at",
            "optionA": "  Arcot ",
            "optionB": "  Jhansi ",
            "optionC": "  Plassey ",
            "optionD": "  Wandiwash ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Wandiwash was a decisive battle in India during the Seven Years' War. The Count de Lally's army, burdened by a lack of naval support and funds, attempted to regain the fort at Vandavasi, now in Tamil Nadu. This was the Third Carnatic War fought between the French and the British. ",
            "keyString": "490540s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct related to the Charter Act of 1793?\nI. Renewed the Charter of the Company for 20 more years.\nII. Regulated the finances of the Company.\nIII. Lay down that the salaries of the Board of Control and their staffs were to be paid from the British revenues.\nIV. Prohibited the Commander-in-Chief from being a member of the Governor General's Council",
            "optionA": "  I, II & III ",
            "optionB": "  I, II & IV ",
            "optionC": "  I & II ",
            "optionD": "  II & III ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe statements that are correct related to the Charter Act of 1793 were Renewed the Charter of the Company for 20 more years. Regulated the finances of the Company. Prohibited the Commander-in-Chief from being a member of the Governor General's Council. ",
            "keyString": "490574s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The correct Chronological order in which the British established their trading centre in the places mentioned below is",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta, Bombay, Madras, Surat ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay, Madras, Surat, Calcutta ",
            "optionC": "  Surat, Madras, Bombay, Calcutta ",
            "optionD": "  Surat, Madras, Calcutta, Bombay ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t1613-14: British East India Company set up trading post at Surat1639: The local king of Madras granted the Company a lease1662: King Charles II of England was given Bombay as dowry after marrying the Portuguese princess and1667: The English obtained the royal farm to trade in Bengal from the Mughal Emperor Aurangzeb. The three small villages in the east of India called Sutanati, Gobindapore and Kalikata were renamed Calcutta in 1690.",
            "keyString": "490594s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Punjab was annexed to the British empire during the reign of Governor General",
            "optionA": "  Lord Bentinck ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Cornwallis ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Canning ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the reign of Dalhousie East India Company annexed Punjab in 1849. Most of the Punjab region was annexed by the East India Company in 1849, and was one of the last areas of the Indian subcontinent to fall under British control. In 1858, the Punjab, along with the rest of British India, came under the direct rule of the British crown. ",
            "keyString": "490608s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who of the following Governor General is associated with Subsidiary Alliance System?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Cornwallies ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Wellesley ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Mayo ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Delhousie ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Subsidiary Alliance System was \u201cNon-Intervention Policy\u201d used by Lord Wellesley who was the Governor-General (1798-1805) to establish British Empire in India. According to this system, every ruler in India had to accept to pay a subsidy to the British for the maintenance of British army. ",
            "keyString": "490621s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bengal British India Society founded in Calcutta on 20 April 1843, was the __________ political public association to be formed in British India, the first being the zamindari association (1837)",
            "optionA": "  First ",
            "optionB": "  Second ",
            "optionC": "  Third ",
            "optionD": "  Fourth ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBengal British India Society founded in Calcutta on 20 April 1843, was the Second political public association to be formed in British India, the first being the zamindari association (1837). ",
            "keyString": "532290s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Government of India __________, the British Crown assumed direct administration of India in the new British Raj",
            "optionA": "  Act of 1658 ",
            "optionB": "  Act of 1758 ",
            "optionC": "  Act of 1858 ",
            "optionD": "  Act of 1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGovernment of India Act 1858 was passed on August 2, 1858. Its provisions called for the liquidation of the British East India Company (who had up to this point been ruling British India under the auspices of Parliament) and the transference of its functions to the British Crown. ",
            "keyString": "532328s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The East India Association was founded by __________ in 1866",
            "optionA": "  Lord Lyveden ",
            "optionB": "  Raja radhakanta dev ",
            "optionC": "  Debendranath Tagore ",
            "optionD": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe East India Association was founded by Dadabhai Naoroji in 1866, in collaboration with Indians and retired British officials in London. It superseded the London Indian Society and was a platform for discussing matters and ideas about India, and to provide representation for Indians to the Government. ",
            "keyString": "532345s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following Indian cracks the British Indian Civil Services Examination in the first time of Indian History?",
            "optionA": "  Satyendranath Tagore ",
            "optionB": "  R. ",
            "optionC": " Dutt ",
            "optionD": "  Behari Lal Gupta ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSatyendranath Tagore became first Indian who cracked I.C.S. or Indian Civil Service examination. ",
            "keyString": "532361s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term of office fixed by Regulating Act for Governor General was",
            "optionA": "  4 years ",
            "optionB": "  5 years ",
            "optionC": "  3 years ",
            "optionD": "  2 years ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Regulating Act ( May 3, 1773): In 1765, after the battle of Buxer the East India Company got the Diwani ( Right to collect Revenue) of Bengal , Bihar and Orissa. The Governor General was assisted by four councilors. Their tenure of office was fixed for 5 years. ",
            "keyString": "532375s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The only Viceroy to be assassinated in India was",
            "optionA": "  Lord Harding ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Northbrook ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Ellenborough ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Mayo ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Mayo was killed by an Afridi Pathan Sher Ali Afridi in Port Blair of Andaman and Nicobar on 8th Feb, 1972. ",
            "keyString": "571955s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "British Indian Association was founded on October 29, 1851 at__________",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionB": "  Pune ",
            "optionC": "  Madras ",
            "optionD": "  Bombay ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe British Indian Association was founded on October 29, 1851 at Calcutta with Raja Radhakanta Dev and Debendranath Tagore as its President and Secretary respectively. Other members of the Association included Ramgopal Ghosh, Peary Chand Mitra and Krishnadas Pal. Its membership was kept exclusive to Indians. ",
            "keyString": "571990s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who defeated the Spanish Armada?",
            "optionA": "  Elizabeth I ",
            "optionB": "  Elizabeth II ",
            "optionC": "  Henry VIII ",
            "optionD": "  James I ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe defeat of the Spanish Armada in 1588 has long been held as one of England's greatest military achievements. The successful defence of the kingdom against invasion on such an unprecedented scale boosted the prestige of England's Queen Elizabeth I and encouraged a sense of English pride and nationalism. ",
            "keyString": "572008s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which British Governor General introduced Postage Stamp in India?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Auckland ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Canning ",
            "optionD": "  Lord William Bentinck ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Dalhousie introduced Postage stamp, he also introduced Railway, Telegram and PWD. ",
            "keyString": "572021s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following British persons admitted the Revolt of 1857 as a national revolt?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Canning ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Ellenborough ",
            "optionD": "  Disraeli ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBritish member of Parliament (House of commons) Benziman Disraeli admitted the revolt of 1857 as a National Revolt. V. D. SavarKar describe this revolt as the Indian's first struggle for Independence. ",
            "keyString": "572034s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The greatest contribution of the British rule to the growth of India nationalism was the __________",
            "optionA": "  Introduction of western education in India ",
            "optionB": "  Racial arrogance of the British ",
            "optionC": "  Denial of Higher Jobs to deserving Indians ",
            "optionD": "  Queen's proclamation of 1858 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIntroduction of western education was another important factor which paved the way for the growth of nationalism. Three main agencies were responsible for the spread of modem education in India. They were the foreign Christian missionaries, the British Government and the progressive Indians. ",
            "keyString": "606543s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the Viceroyalty of Sir John Lawrence the bone of contention between India and Bhutan was",
            "optionA": "  Duars ",
            "optionB": "  Jalpaiguri ",
            "optionC": "  Goalpara ",
            "optionD": "  Cooch Behar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the Viceroyalty of Sir John Lawrence the bone of contention between India and Bhutan wasDuars. ",
            "keyString": "606580s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The arrival of Vasco da Gama in Calicut, India on __________",
            "optionA": "  1398 ",
            "optionB": "  1495 ",
            "optionC": "  1496 ",
            "optionD": "  1498 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVasco Da Gama sailed from Lisbon on July 8, 1497, with a crew of 170 men. He arrived at Calicut (now Kozhikode) on May 20, 1498. ",
            "keyString": "606596s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The island of Bombay had been given to the British Prince Charles II as dowry by the",
            "optionA": "  Dutch ",
            "optionB": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionC": "  Danish ",
            "optionD": "  French ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe island of Bombay had been given to the British Prince Charles II as dowry by the Portuguese. ",
            "keyString": "606610s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): East India Association in London was organised by Dadabhai Naoroji.\nReason (R): He wanted to influence the British public opinion",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R is true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R is true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe East India Association was founded by Dadabhai Naoroji in 1866, in collaboration with Indians and retired British officials in London. It superseded the London Indian Society and was a platform for discussing matters and ideas about India, and to provide representation for Indians to the Government. ",
            "keyString": "606623s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Governor General of India?",
            "optionA": "  Warren Hastings ",
            "optionB": "  William Bentick ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Delhousie ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Canning ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWarren Hastings (6 December 1732 \u2013 22 August 1818), an English statesman, was the first Governor of the Presidency of Fort William (Bengal), the head of the Supreme Council of Bengal, and thereby the first de facto Governor-General of India from 1773 to 1785. The first governor-general in India (of Bengal) was Warren Hastings, the first official governor-general of British India was Lord William Bentinck, and the first governor-general of the Dominion of India was Lord Mountbatten. ",
            "keyString": "644228s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Governor General of Bengal?",
            "optionA": "  Robert Clive ",
            "optionB": "  William Bentinck ",
            "optionC": "  Warren Hasting ",
            "optionD": "  Col. Sanders ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWarren Hastings is the first British Governor General of Bengal. He took the charge as a Governor General on 20th October,1773. ",
            "keyString": "644263s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Viceroy of India was",
            "optionA": "  Lord Canning ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Hardinge ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Elgin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Canning was the first Viceroy of India. The title of Viceroy was created in 1858 after the mutiny of 1857. Before 1858, East India Company was ruling large parts of India and the head of administration of the East India Company was called Governor General. ",
            "keyString": "644280s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After the year 1853, a substantial amount of British capital had been invested in",
            "optionA": "  Tea Plantations ",
            "optionB": "  The Railways ",
            "optionC": "  Coal Mining ",
            "optionD": "  Jute Mills ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter the year 1853, a substantial amount of British capital had been invested in the railways. ",
            "keyString": "644294s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The British Governor General and Viceroy who served for the longest period in India was",
            "optionA": "  Lord Irwin ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Linlithgow ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe British Governor General and Viceroy who served for the longest period in India wasLord Dalhousie. ",
            "keyString": "644307s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following analysed the causes of the uprising of 1857 advocating a reconciliation between the British and the Muslims?",
            "optionA": "  Sayyed Ahmad Brelvi ",
            "optionB": "  Shah Waliullah ",
            "optionC": "  Sayyed Ahmad Khan ",
            "optionD": "  Sayyed Amir Ali ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the Indian Rebellion of 1857, he remained, loyal to the British Empire and was noted for his actions in saving European lives. After the rebellion, he penned the booklet 'The Causes of the Indian Mutiny' \u2013 a daring critique, at the time, of British policies that he blamed for causing the revolt. Believing that the future of Muslims was threatened by the rigidity of their orthodox outlook, Sir Syed began promoting Western\u2013style scientific education by founding modern schools and journals and organising Muslim entrepreneurs. ",
            "keyString": "680929s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lytton held an Imperial Durbar at Delhi in 1877 to announce __________ as the Empress of India at a time when a large part of the country was in the grip of a severe famine",
            "optionA": "  Queen Elizabeth ",
            "optionB": "  Queen Victoria ",
            "optionC": "  Queen Anne ",
            "optionD": "  Queen Marie ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLytton held an Imperial Durbar at Delhi in 1877 to announce Queen Victoria as the Empress of India at a time when a large part of the country was in the grip of a severe famine. ",
            "keyString": "680963s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During British rule, who was instrumental for the introduction of the Ryotwari system in the then Madras Presidency?",
            "optionA": "  Macaulay ",
            "optionB": "  Elphinstone ",
            "optionC": "  Thomas Munro ",
            "optionD": "  John Lawrence ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThomas Munro and Captain Reid known as the father of the Ryotwari Settlement in India. It was firstly introduced in district 'BARAMAHAL' of Tamilnadu. By this settlement the Ryott-Cultivator was recognised as a owner of field and he had to pay revenue to British Government directly. ",
            "keyString": "680977s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The East India Company was established in the year",
            "optionA": "  1607 AD ",
            "optionB": "  1600 AD ",
            "optionC": "  1700 AD ",
            "optionD": "  1669 AD ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe East India Company was an English company formed for the exploitation of trade with East and Southeast Asia and India. Incorporated by royal charter on December 31, 1600, it was started as a monopolistic trading body so that England could participate in the East Indian spice trade. ",
            "keyString": "680989s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 'Sepoy Mutiny' was in the year __________",
            "optionA": "  1657 ",
            "optionB": "  1757 ",
            "optionC": "  1765 ",
            "optionD": "  1857 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Mutiny, also called Sepoy Mutiny, widespread but unsuccessful rebellion against British rule in India in 1857\u201358. Begun in Meerut by Indian troops (sepoys) in the service of the British East India Company, it spread to Delhi, Agra, Kanpur, and Lucknow. ",
            "keyString": "680999s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Indian ruler had requested Napoleon for help in driving the British away from India?",
            "optionA": "  Shivaji ",
            "optionB": "  Jai Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Tipu Sultan ",
            "optionD": "  Rani of Jhansi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTipu Sultan had requested Napoleon for help in driving the British away from India. ",
            "keyString": "727885s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rani Laxmi Bai died fighting the British in the Battle of",
            "optionA": "  Jhansi ",
            "optionB": "  Kanpur ",
            "optionC": "  Gwalior ",
            "optionD": "  Kalpi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn June 18th 1858, Rani Lakshmibai of Jhansi, one of the most important figures of India's First War of Independence, died while fighting against the British in Gwalior. ",
            "keyString": "727981s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year was the title of Governor general chanced to that of the Viceroy?",
            "optionA": "  1858 ",
            "optionB": "  1861 ",
            "optionC": "  1878 ",
            "optionD": "  1885 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe title \"Viceroy and Governor-General\" was first used in the queen's proclamation appointing Viscount Canning in 1858. ",
            "keyString": "727995s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mutiny was brought to an end with the fall of __________ into the hands of the British in India",
            "optionA": "  Meerut ",
            "optionB": "  Awadh ",
            "optionC": "  Gwalior ",
            "optionD": "  Rohilkhand ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mutiny was brought to an end with the fall of Gwalior into the hands of the British in India. ",
            "keyString": "728007s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The permanent settlement was made in Bengal in the sphere of revenue administration by",
            "optionA": "  William Pitt ",
            "optionB": "  Hastings ",
            "optionC": "  William Bentic ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Cornwallis ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Permanent Settlement (also Premanent Settlement of Bengal) was introduced by Lord Cornwallis in 1793. It was an agreement between the British East India Company and the Landlords of Bengal to settle the Land Revenue to be raised. ",
            "keyString": "728018s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are correct related to the Revolt of the Bhils?\nI. The Bhils revolted in 1818 due to the occupation of their territory by the British.\nII. They defied British authority for 50 years from 1818.\nIII. Their revolt was finally ended by the British through military operations as well as conciliatory measures.\nIV. The leader of the Bhil revolt was Ram Charan",
            "optionA": "  I & II ",
            "optionB": "  II & III ",
            "optionC": "  I & III ",
            "optionD": "  II & IV ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe statements that are correct related to the Revolt of the Bhils are They defied British authority for 50 years from 1818. Their revolt was finally ended by the British through military operations as well as conciliatory measures. ",
            "keyString": "764271s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gandhi had been provoked into crusading for the lot of the Asians in South Africa by the British law called the Act",
            "optionA": "  Apartheid ",
            "optionB": "  Blacks' Registration ",
            "optionC": "  cl Asiatic Registration ",
            "optionD": "  Subcitizens' Licence ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi had been provoked into crusading for the lot of the Asians in South Africa by the British law called cl Asiatic Registration. ",
            "keyString": "764307s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where had civil rebellions against the British initially started?",
            "optionA": "  Uttar Pradesh and Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Bengal and Bihar ",
            "optionC": "  Odisha ",
            "optionD": "  Madras and Calcutta ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe civil rebellions against the British was initially started at Uttar Pradesh and Madhya Pradesh. ",
            "keyString": "764321s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the Viceroy when Delhi became the capital of British India?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Minto ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Hardinge ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Wavell ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCharles Hardingewas the Viceroy when the capital of India was shifted from Calcutta (now Kolkata) to Delhi in 1911. There is a well known medical college in Delhi named after the Viceroy. ",
            "keyString": "764334s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Joseph Fran\u00e7ois Dupleix was the commander of the __________ forces in India",
            "optionA": "  French ",
            "optionB": "  British ",
            "optionC": "  American ",
            "optionD": "  Dutch ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJoseph-Francois Dupleix was a colonial administrator and governor-general of the French territories in India, who nearly realized his dream of establishing a French empire in India. ",
            "keyString": "764345s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the first hundred years of the British rule in India, people's resentment and opposition to the British policies mainly surfaced in the form of",
            "optionA": "  Tribal uprisings ",
            "optionB": "  Peasant uprisings ",
            "optionC": "  Civil uprisings ",
            "optionD": "  Both A and B above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the first hundred years of the British rule in India, people's resentment and opposition to the British policies mainly surfaced in the form of tribal uprisings, peasant uprisings. ",
            "keyString": "801696s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Permanent Settlement was enforced on__________",
            "optionA": "  1693 ",
            "optionB": "  1793 ",
            "optionC": "  1893 ",
            "optionD": "  1933 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe rules of the permanent settlement made every individual zamindar and talukdar the permanent and absolute proprietors of the land under their control. As absolute proprietors of land, zamindars and talukdars were required to pay revenue to government at a rate fixed permanently. ",
            "keyString": "801727s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who set up the dual system of administration in Bengal?",
            "optionA": "  Robert Clive ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Wellesley ",
            "optionC": "  Dupleix ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Macaulay ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Dual System of Government in Bengal was the brainchild of Lord Clive. ",
            "keyString": "801741s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "MSP means __________",
            "optionA": "  Malabar Special Police ",
            "optionB": "  Mysore Special police ",
            "optionC": "  Madras Special police ",
            "optionD": "  Mappila Special Police ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Malabar Special Police (MSP) is a paramilitary unit of the State Police of Kerala. ",
            "keyString": "801754s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lord Lytton had lowered the age limit for Indian for the ICS from 21 year to",
            "optionA": "  20 years ",
            "optionB": "  19 years ",
            "optionC": "  18 years ",
            "optionD": "  17 years ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe age for eligibility in civil services was brought down from 21 to 19 years by Lord Lytton. ",
            "keyString": "801766s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arrange the following in chronological order:\nI. Viceroy Lytton\nII. Viceroy Mayo\nIII. Viceroy Lansdowne\nIV. Viceroy Linlithgow",
            "optionA": "  II, III, I, IV ",
            "optionB": "  II, I, III, IV ",
            "optionC": "  IV, III, II, I ",
            "optionD": "  III, IV, I, II ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tViceroy Mayo- Richard Southwell Bourke, 6th Earl of Mayo, KP, GCSI, PC, styled Lord Naas between 1842 and 1867, called Lord Mayo in India, was a statesman, Viceroy of India and prominent member of the British Conservative Party from Dublin, Ireland. Viceroy Lytton- Robert Bulwer-Lytton, 1st Earl of Lytton GCB GCSI GCIE PC was an English statesman, Conservative politician, and poet. He served as Viceroy of India between 1876 and 1880 - during his tenure as which Queen Victoria was proclaimed Empress of India - and as British Ambassador to France from 1887 to 1891. Viceroy Lansdowne- Henry Charles Keith Petty-Fitzmaurice, 5th Marquess of Lansdowne, KG, GCSI, GCMG, GCIE, PC was a British statesman who served successively as the fifth Governor General of Canada, Viceroy of India, Secretary of State for War, and Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. Viceroy Linlithgow- Victor Alexander John Hope, 2nd Marquess of Linlithgow, KG, KT, FRSE, GCSI, GCIE, OBE was a British Unionist politician, agriculturalist and colonial administrator. He served as Governor-General and Viceroy of India from 1936 to 1943. He was usually referred to simply as Linlithgow. ",
            "keyString": "843417s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Hindu Widows Remarriage Act __________",
            "optionA": "  1856 ",
            "optionB": "  1858 ",
            "optionC": "  1865 ",
            "optionD": "  1946 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Hindu Widows Remarriage Act of 1856, provided legal safeguards against loss of certain forms of inheritance for remarrying a Hindu widow, though, under the Act, the widow forsook any inheritance due her from her deceased husband. ",
            "keyString": "843460s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. Bengal Nawab was captured and put to death by Mir Jafar in the Battle of Plassey, 1757.\nII. After Mir Qasim, Nizam-ud-daula was made the Nawab of Bengal.\nIII. The same person acted as the deputy Dewan on behalf of the East Indian Company and as Deputy Subedar on behalf of the Bengal Nawab.\nIV. In 1767, British Government ordered the East India Company to pay \u00a3400,000 per year.\nWhich of these statement(s) is/are correct related to the Bengal Politics during the 18th century?",
            "optionA": "  I & II ",
            "optionB": "  I & III ",
            "optionC": "  II & IV ",
            "optionD": "  III & IV ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe same person acted as deputy Dewan on behalf of the East Indian Company and as Deputy Subedar on behalf of the Bengal Nawab. The British East India Company was suffering from massive amounts of debts incurred primarily from annual contractual payments due to the British government totaling \u00a3400,000 per year. ",
            "keyString": "843478s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What did the Hunter Commission appointed by the Viceroy probe?",
            "optionA": "  Bardoli Satyagraha ",
            "optionB": "  Khilafat Agitation ",
            "optionC": "  Jallianwala Bagh tragedy ",
            "optionD": "  Chauri Chaura incident ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter Jallianwala Bagh tragedy a commission was estb. under William Wilson Hunter in 1919. It is known as Hunter commission but the report of commission was rejected by INC,and new commission was estb. under Madan Mohan Malviya. ",
            "keyString": "843497s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The British colonial policies in India proved most ruinous for Indian",
            "optionA": "  agriculture ",
            "optionB": "  trade ",
            "optionC": "  industry ",
            "optionD": "  handicrafts ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe british colonial policies in india proved most ruinous for indian handicrafts. The real blow to Indian handicrafts fell after 1813, when they lost not only their foreign markets but, what was of much greater importance, their market in India itself. The Industrial Revolution in Britain completely transformed Britain\u2019s economy and its economic relations with India. ",
            "keyString": "843511s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Indian to be elected as a member of the British House of Commons was",
            "optionA": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionB": "  Surendra Nath Banerjee ",
            "optionC": "  Dr. BR Ambedkar ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDadabhai Naoroji was elected to the British house of commons from the Finsbury Central Constituency in the elections of 1892 by a narrow margin of 3 votes by defeating Fredrick Thomas Penton. Being a subject of the British crown (Being a citizen of British India) he was allowed to take part in the election. ",
            "keyString": "885367s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Indian to contest an election to the British House of Commons was",
            "optionA": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionB": "  Womesh Chandra Banerjee ",
            "optionC": "  Surendranath Banerjee ",
            "optionD": "  Pheroze Shah Mehta ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Indian to contest an election to the British House of Commons was Womesh Chandra Banerjee. ",
            "keyString": "885402s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Bengali Drama, written to highlight the brutality of the British indigo planters, was",
            "optionA": "  Rast Goftar ",
            "optionB": "  Neel Darpan ",
            "optionC": "  Shome Prakash ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNil Darpan (The Indigo Mirror) is a Bengali play written by Dinabandhu Mitra in 1858\u20131859. The play was published in Dhaka in 1860, under a pseudonym of the author. The play was essential to Nil Vidroha, better known as the Indigo Revolt of February\u2013March 1859 in Bengal, when farmers refused to sow indigo in their fields to protest against exploitative farming under the British Raj. ",
            "keyString": "885418s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Treaty of Lahore was signed between the Sikhs and the British in India in the year",
            "optionA": "  1836 ",
            "optionB": "  1846 ",
            "optionC": "  1856 ",
            "optionD": "  1866 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Treaty of Lahore was signed on 9 March 1846 after the First Sikh War. After the defeat of the Sikhs at the Battle of Sobraon the British were able to march into Lahore without any further battles. After the British reached the city of Lahore the treaty was signed. ",
            "keyString": "885433s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The privileges of free trade granted to the English East India Company were confirmed in 1717 by Emperor",
            "optionA": "  Bahadur Shah ",
            "optionB": "  Farrukh-Siyar ",
            "optionC": "  Muhammad Shah ",
            "optionD": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEmperor Farrukhsiyar issued the British East India Company such a farman in 1717. It allowed the Company to live and trade for free in Mughal India except for an annual payment. They were also given the right to issue dastak or trade permits to transfer goods, which the officials largely used for their own gains. ",
            "keyString": "885446s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following British official associated with the local self-government?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Mayo ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Dufferin ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Northbrook ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Ripon ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Ripon is known to have granted the Indians first taste of freedom by introducing the Local Self Government in 1882. His scheme of local self government developed the Municipal institutions which had been growing up in the country ever since India was occupied by the British Crown. ",
            "keyString": "928570s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Year of the Battle of Wandiwash is __________",
            "optionA": "  1560 ",
            "optionB": "  1660 ",
            "optionC": "  1760 ",
            "optionD": "  1860 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBattle of Wandiwash, (Jan. 22, 1760), in the history of India, a confrontation between the French, under the comte de Lally, and the British, under Sir Eyre Coote. It was the decisive battle in the Anglo-French struggle in southern India during the Seven Years War (1756\u201363). ",
            "keyString": "928604s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Charter for the establishment of the East India Company was granted by",
            "optionA": "  Queen Elizabeth I ",
            "optionB": "  Queen Anbolin ",
            "optionC": "  Queen Mary ",
            "optionD": "  Queen Victoria ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCharter granted to the East India Company. Queen Elizabeth I of England grants a formal charter to the London merchants trading to the East Indies, hoping to break the Dutch monopoly of the spice trade in what is now Indonesia. ",
            "keyString": "928620s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By the Act of 1773, Parliament granted a loan of __________ to the East India Company",
            "optionA": "  Rs. 480,000 ",
            "optionB": "  Rs. 400,000 ",
            "optionC": "  Rs. 500,000 ",
            "optionD": "  Rs. 300,000 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBy the Act of 1773, Parliament granted a loan of Rs. 400,000 to the East India Company. ",
            "keyString": "928633s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): In some places artisans and craftsmen participated in the Revolt of 1857.\nReason (R): The British policy of 'one-way' free trade destroyed village industries and handicrafts in India",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R is true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R is true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArtisans and craftsmen were ruined by the large-scale influx of cheap British. ",
            "keyString": "928645s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During colonial period, British capital was mainly invested in",
            "optionA": "  Infra structure ",
            "optionB": "  Industry ",
            "optionC": "  Agriculture ",
            "optionD": "  Services ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAgriculture was mainly invested by British during colonial period, the raw material related to agriculture was compulsory for industry during colonial period. ",
            "keyString": "970859s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The British attitude towards granting India independence changed partly owing to the",
            "optionA": "  Change in the government of the UK ",
            "optionB": "  Impact of World War II ",
            "optionC": "  Growing tide of Indian Nationalism ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe British attitude towards granting India independence changed partly owing to the Change in the government of the UK, Impact of World War II, Growing tide of Indian Nationalism. ",
            "keyString": "970895s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1650 Gabriel Boughton, an employee of the Company obtained a license for trade in __________",
            "optionA": "  Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Orissa ",
            "optionC": "  Mysore ",
            "optionD": "  Surat ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1650, Gabriel Boughton an employee of the Company obtained a license for trade in Bengal. An English factory was set up in 1651 at Hugli. ",
            "keyString": "970913s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'We do not seek our independence out of Britain's ruin' said",
            "optionA": "  Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Gokhale ",
            "optionD": "  Rabindranath Tagore ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIts true that Gandhi did have a compromising attitude towards the British during WWII and even stated that \"We do not seek independence out of Britain's ruin\". Though Gandhi was the most influential figure in the political scenario at the time, it's important to remember that simply because he wanted to maintain a compromising attittude towards the British, many of the other political leaders of the time did not wish to do so. ",
            "keyString": "970926s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The East India Company had taken Bombay from",
            "optionA": "  The Dutch ",
            "optionB": "  Charles I ",
            "optionC": "  Charles II ",
            "optionD": "  The Portuguese ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe East India Company had taken Bombay from Charles II. On 21 May 1662, the marriage treaty of Charles II of England and Catherine of Braganza, daughter of King John IV of Portugal, placed Bombay in possession of the British Empire, as part of dowry of Catherine to Charles. ",
            "keyString": "970939s44m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Indian Governor of a British Province (Bihar) in India was",
            "optionA": "  Sir SP Sinha ",
            "optionB": "  Sir Shaukat Hayat ",
            "optionC": "  Sir Hari Singh Gaur ",
            "optionD": "  VJ Patel ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHe was the first Governor of Bihar and Orissa, first Indian Advocate-General of Bengal, first Indian to become a member of the Viceroy's executive Council and the first Indian to become a member of the British ministry. He is sometimes also referred as Satyendra Prasanno Sinha or Satyendra Prasad Sinha. ",
            "keyString": "18058s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not the provision of The Act of 1892?",
            "optionA": "  A simultaneous examination of ICS to be held in England and India ",
            "optionB": "  Reforms of the legislative council and adoption of the principle of election in place of nomination ",
            "optionC": "  Support of the annexation of Upper Burma ",
            "optionD": "  Reduction in the Military expenditure ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBurma achieved independence from British rule on 4 January 1948. ",
            "keyString": "18258s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "August Offer 1940 was made by the Viceroy",
            "optionA": "  Willingdon ",
            "optionB": "  Linlithgow ",
            "optionC": "  Minto ",
            "optionD": "  Lytton ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 8 August 1940, early in the Battle of Britain, the Viceroy of India, Lord Linlithgow, made the so-called \"August Offer\". ",
            "keyString": "18430s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The British introduced the railways in India in order to",
            "optionA": "  Promote heavy industries in India ",
            "optionB": "  Facilitate British commerce and adminitstrative\ncontrol ",
            "optionC": "  More foodstuff in case of famine ",
            "optionD": "  Enable Indians to move freely within the\ncountry ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBritish Introduced the railways in India (1853) to facilitate British commerce and administrative control. ",
            "keyString": "18594s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following according to the correct chronological order of the Governors-General during British India\nI. Wellesley\nII. Marquess of Hastings\nIII. Amherst\nIV. Bentinck",
            "optionA": "  I, II, III & IV ",
            "optionB": "  II, I, IV & III ",
            "optionC": "  I, III, II & IV ",
            "optionD": "  III, I, II & IV ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe correct chronological order of the Governors-General during British India were Wellesley, Marquess of Hastings, Amherst, Bentinck. ",
            "keyString": "18754s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fakir-Sannyasi Resistance against the East India Company dominated in __________",
            "optionA": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Kerala ",
            "optionC": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionD": "  Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFakir-Sannyasi Resistance an armed resistance of the combined body of Muslim fakirs (sufis) and Hindu sannyasis (yogis) against the dominance of the English East India Company in Bengal. This resistance began in 1760 and continued for more than four decades. ",
            "keyString": "61331s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): The announcement of the Simon Commission aroused widespread Indian resentment. \nReason (R): The British Government in defiance of the opinion of all parties in India had deliberately decided to appoint an all British Commission",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R is true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R is true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe British Government in defiance of the opinion of all parties in India had deliberately decided to appoint an all British Commission. ",
            "keyString": "61526s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Treaty of Mangalore was in the year __________",
            "optionA": "  1484 ",
            "optionB": "  1584 ",
            "optionC": "  1684 ",
            "optionD": "  1784 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Treaty of Mangalore was signed between Tipu Sultan and the British East India Company on 11 March 1784. It was signed in Mangalore and brought an end to the Second Anglo-Mysore War. ",
            "keyString": "61664s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During their rule the British persuaded or forced cultivators in Assam to grow__________",
            "optionA": "  Jute ",
            "optionB": "  Tea ",
            "optionC": "  Sugarcane ",
            "optionD": "  Wheat ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe trade of tea was most profitable to Britishers that's why they turned to cultivator in Assam to grow Tea. ",
            "keyString": "61785s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On which day had premier Attlee conceded that the British would quit India by June, 1948?",
            "optionA": "  January 26, 1947 ",
            "optionB": "  August 15, 1947 ",
            "optionC": "  January 26, 1948 ",
            "optionD": "  February 20, 1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFebruary 20, 1947 had premier Attlee conceded that the British would quit India by June, 1948. ",
            "keyString": "61899s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following events did not take place during the Viceroyalty of Lord Curzon?",
            "optionA": "  Establishment of the department of Archaeology ",
            "optionB": "  Second Delhi Durbar ",
            "optionC": "  Formation of Indian National Congress ",
            "optionD": "  Partition of Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian National congress was fromed in 1885 during the Viceroyalty of Lord Dufferin. The first Chairman of INC was W. C. Banerjee.",
            "keyString": "154511s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Simla Conference called by Viceroy Lord Wavell (to discuss the so-called Wavell Plan) in June 1945 failed on account of",
            "optionA": "  Jinnah's demand that the Muslim League alone would nominate Muslim members to the Executive Council ",
            "optionB": "  the demand of the Congress to include the members of all communities in their quota to the Executive Council ",
            "optionC": "  the demand of the Scheduled Castes to reserved seats in the Executive Council in Proportion to their population ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Simla Conference called by Viceroy Lord Wavell (to discuss the so-called Wavell Plan) in June 1945 failed on account of Jinnah's demand that the Muslim League alone would nominate Muslim members to the Executive Council, the demand of the Congress to include the members of all communities in their quota to the Executive Council, the demand of the Scheduled Castes to reserved seats in the Executive Council in Proportion to their population. ",
            "keyString": "154546s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lord Cornwallis had introduced the __________ land tenure system",
            "optionA": "  Zamindari ",
            "optionB": "  Ryotwari ",
            "optionC": "  Mahalwari ",
            "optionD": "  Inamdari ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tImmediately after putting his legs in India, Lord Cornwallis in 1786 opined once-for-all settlement with the zamindars for the collection of land revenue. In fact, Lord Cornwallis cut the Gordian knot in 1790 when the decennial permanent settlement system was decided to be introduced in Bengal, Bihar, and Orissa. ",
            "keyString": "154563s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lytton was selected as Viceroy to India to fulfill the ambitious plans of Disraeli in __________",
            "optionA": "  Awadh ",
            "optionB": "  Afghanistan ",
            "optionC": "  Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Burma ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLytton was selected as Viceroy to India to fulfill the ambitious plans of Disraeli in Afghanistan. ",
            "keyString": "154577s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said that the exploitative nature of British rule was 'Bleeding India White'?",
            "optionA": "  Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionC": "  Hume ",
            "optionD": "  Annie Besant ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDadabhai Naoroji said that the exploitative nature of British rule was 'Bleeding India White'. ",
            "keyString": "154590s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following act of India ensured the partition of India?",
            "optionA": "  Government of India Act, 1909 ",
            "optionB": "  Government of India Act, 1919 ",
            "optionC": "  Government of India Act, 1935 ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt was passed to expand participation of Indians in the government of India. The Act embodied the reforms recommended in the report of the Secretary of State for India, Edwin Montagu, and the Viceroy, Lord Chemlsford. The Act covered ten years, from 1919 to 1929. The Act received royal assent on 23 December 1919. ",
            "keyString": "197762s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following British official intiated the Doctrine of Lapse?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Wellesley ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Auckland ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "optionD": "  Warren Hastings ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe policy is most commonly associated with Lord Dalhousie, who was the Governor General of the East India Company in India between 1848 and 1856. ",
            "keyString": "197798s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The exclusive right of trading between __________ was granted to the East India Company",
            "optionA": "  North America and South America ",
            "optionB": "  Red Sea and Caspian Sea ",
            "optionC": "  The Cape of Good Hope and the Straits of Magellan ",
            "optionD": "  France and Poland ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe exclusive right of trading between The Cape of Good Hope and the Straits of Magellan was granted to the East India Company. ",
            "keyString": "197815s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Despite holding a monopoly, the East India Company had faced competition from what it had termed as the 'interlopers' represented by the",
            "optionA": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionB": "  Indigenous merchants ",
            "optionC": "  British free merchants ",
            "optionD": "  Dutch ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDespite holding a monopoly, the East India Company had faced competition from what it had termed as the 'interlopers' represented by theBritish free merchants. ",
            "keyString": "197829s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Act constituting the first legislative interference by the British Parliament in the affairs of India was the",
            "optionA": "  Fox's India Act, 1783 ",
            "optionB": "  Pitt's India Act, 1784 ",
            "optionC": "  Regulating Act, 1773 ",
            "optionD": "  Declaratory Act, 1781 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Regulating Act 1773 was an Act of the Parliament of Great Britain intended to overhaul the management of the East India Company's rule in India. ",
            "keyString": "197841s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The United East India Company refers to the company in India formed by the",
            "optionA": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionB": "  Dutch ",
            "optionC": "  French ",
            "optionD": "  British ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe United East Indian Company (Dutch: Vereenigde Oost-Indische Compagnie; VOC), referred to by the British as the Dutch East India Company, was originally established as a chartered company in 1602, when the Dutch government granted it a 21-year monopoly on Dutch spice trade. ",
            "keyString": "242175s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The new proletariat class which emerged in India on account of the British economic policies, consisted of",
            "optionA": "  Money lenders ",
            "optionB": "  Landlords ",
            "optionC": "  Traders ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe new proletariat class which emerged in India on account of the British economic policies, consisted of Money lenders, Landlords, Traders. ",
            "keyString": "242209s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At which place in Bengal was the East India Company given permission to trade and build a factory by the Mughals in 1651 ?",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionB": "  Qasim Bazar ",
            "optionC": "  Singur ",
            "optionD": "  Burdwan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt Qasim Bazar in Bengal was the East India Company given permission to trade and build a factory by the Mughals in 1651. East India Company established a factory at Qasim Bazar by thepermission Mughals in 1651. ",
            "keyString": "242224s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per 'August Offer' the British objective for India was __________",
            "optionA": "  Dominion Status ",
            "optionB": "  Puma Swaraj ",
            "optionC": "  Responsible Government ",
            "optionD": "  Provincial Authority ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe August Offer was a proposal made by the British government in 1940 promising the expansion of the Executive Council of the Viceroy of India to include more Indians, the establishment of an advisory war council, giving full weight to minority opinion, and the recognition of Indians' right to frame their own constitution (after the end of the war). The Congress rejected the August Offer. Nehru said, \u201cDominion status concept is dead as a door nail.\u201d Gandhi said that the declaration had widened the gulf between the nationalists and the British rulers. ",
            "keyString": "242237s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had, while fasting in the prison, written to the British governor, The individual must die so that the nation may live. Today, I must die so that India may win freedom and glory?",
            "optionA": "  Jatin Das ",
            "optionB": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionC": "  MK Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  SC Bose ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJatin Das, while fasting in the prison, written to the British governor, The individual must die so that the nation may live. Today, I must die so that India may win freedom and glory. ",
            "keyString": "242248s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the period of which Governor General Viceroy was the Indian Civil Service introduced?",
            "optionA": "  Dalhousie ",
            "optionB": "  Curzon ",
            "optionC": "  Bentick ",
            "optionD": "  Conrnwallis ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCornwallis realised that in order to consolidate the British rule in India, it was very important to organise the civil services. Civil Services was started by Lord Cornwallis and hence he is called the \u201cFather of Indian Civil Service\u201d. ",
            "keyString": "284670s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said that he had not become His Majesty's first Minister to preside over the liquidation of the British Empire?",
            "optionA": "  Attlee ",
            "optionB": "  Churchill ",
            "optionC": "  Disraeli ",
            "optionD": "  Loyd George ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChurchill said that the Charter did not apply to India, for he had 'not become His Majesty's first minister to preside over the liquidation of the British empire'. ",
            "keyString": "284718s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following authorised the British Government to imprison any person without trial and conviction in a court of law",
            "optionA": "  Rowlatt Act of 1919 ",
            "optionB": "  Government of India Act of 1935 ",
            "optionC": "  Indian Council Act of 1909 ",
            "optionD": "  Government of India Act of 1919 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per the Rowlatt act the govemment had the power to arrest any person without showing any reason, the acts were threat to the civil liberties. Later, this act became the reason for occurrence of Jallianwala Bagh Tragedy. ",
            "keyString": "284735s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Seven Years' War (1756-1763) resulted in the defeat of the__________ forces",
            "optionA": "  American ",
            "optionB": "  British ",
            "optionC": "  French ",
            "optionD": "  Russian ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1756, the British formally declared war against France. In addition, Spanish attempts to aid France in the Americas had failed, and France also suffered defeats against British forces in India. The Seven Years' War ended with the signing of the treaties of Hubertusburg and Paris in February 1763. ",
            "keyString": "284752s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India became independent during the vice royalty of",
            "optionA": "  William Bentinck ",
            "optionB": "  Wellesley ",
            "optionC": "  Wavell ",
            "optionD": "  Mountbatten ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Mountbatten: Last Viceroy of India (1947-1948) Lord Mountbatten served as last Viceroy of India from 12 February 1947 \u2013 15 August 1947; and then first Governor General of Free India from 15 August 1947 \u2013 21 June 1948. During his tenure, India got independence in the form of two dominions of India Pakistan. ",
            "keyString": "284768s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Governor General had entertained Ranjit Singh with great honour at Ropar?",
            "optionA": "  Minto-I ",
            "optionB": "  William Bentinck ",
            "optionC": "  Hastings ",
            "optionD": "  Auckland ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Governor General William Bentinck had entertained Ranjit Singh with great honour at Ropar. ",
            "keyString": "325629s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is not correct about the provisions of the Government of India Act,1858?",
            "optionA": "  The Queen's Principal Secretary of State received the powers and duties of the Company's Court of Directors ",
            "optionB": "  A council of fifteen members was appointed to assist the Secretary of State for India ",
            "optionC": "  For all the communications between Britain and India, the Secretary of State became the real channel ",
            "optionD": "  All the above statements are incorrect ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Government of India Act 1858 was an Act of the Parliament of the United Kingdom passed on August 2, 1858. Its provisions called for the liquidation of the British East India Company (who had up to this point been ruling British India under the auspices of Parliament) and the transference of its functions to the British Crown. ",
            "keyString": "325669s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not the provision of the government of India Act, 1858?",
            "optionA": "  India was to be governed in the Queen's name ",
            "optionB": "  The Queen's Principal Secretary of State received the powers and duties of the Company's Court of Directors ",
            "optionC": "  Provision for the creation of an Indian Civil Service under the control of the Secretary of State ",
            "optionD": "  The British Parliament was empowered to appoint a Governor-General and the Governors of the Presidencies ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Government of India Act 1858 was an Act of the Parliament of the United Kingdom passed on August 2, 1858. Its provisions called for the liquidation of the British East India Company (who had up to this point been ruling British India under the auspices of Parliament) and the transference of its functions to the British Crown. ",
            "keyString": "325690s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the prime minister of Britain at the time of commencement of the Government of India Act, 1858?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Palmerston ",
            "optionB": "  Russell II ",
            "optionC": "  Edward Smith-Stanley ",
            "optionD": "  Benjamin Disraeli ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Palmerston was the prime minister of Britain at the time of commencement of the Government of India Act, 1858. ",
            "keyString": "325707s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the monarch of Britain at the time of commencement of the Government of India Act, 1858?",
            "optionA": "  William IV ",
            "optionB": "  Victoria ",
            "optionC": "  Edward VII ",
            "optionD": "  George V ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t In August 1858, the British parliament passed an act that set an end to the rule of the company. The control of the British government in India was transferred to the British crown. At this time, Victoria was the queen of Britain. ",
            "keyString": "325722s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Government of India Act/Indian Council Act brought three separate presidencies (Madras, Bombay and Bengal) into a common system?",
            "optionA": "  Indian Council Act of 1861 ",
            "optionB": "  Government of India Act, 1935 ",
            "optionC": "  Government of India Act, 1919 ",
            "optionD": "  Indian Council Act of 1909 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Act for the first time introduced local representation in the Indian government. Rule of company in India ended and the rule of Crown started. The three presidencies (Madras, Bombay and Bengal) were three separate presidencies brought into a common system. ",
            "keyString": "362084s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Treaty of Rajpurghat\" was signed on December 25, 1805 between Holkar and __________",
            "optionA": "  French ",
            "optionB": "  British ",
            "optionC": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionD": "  Dutch ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYashwantrao was the last to sign a treaty with the British, on 24 December 1805 at a place called Rajpur Ghat on the bank of Beas River. The treaty was named 'The Treaty of Peace and Amity between the British Government and Yashwantrao Holkar.' ",
            "keyString": "362119s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The llbert Bill controversy during the period of Lord Ripon exposed the racial bitterness of the British and united the Indians",
            "optionA": "  Lytton ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Ripon ",
            "optionC": "  Queen Elizabeth ",
            "optionD": "  Queen Anne ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBritish subjects in 1873 had been exempted from trial by Indian magistrates, and in cases involving death or transportation they could only be tried by a high court. But by 1883 the viceroy, Lord Ripon, proposed to make British subjects amenable to sessions courts, over which Indians were now senior enough in the civil service to preside. This proposal as embodied in the Ilbert Bill provoked furious protests, especially among the Calcutta (Kolkata) European business community and the Bengal indigo planters, and there was covert sympathy from many officials. ",
            "keyString": "362137s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Peshwaship was abolished by the British at the time of Peshwa",
            "optionA": "  Raghunath Rao ",
            "optionB": "  Narayan Rao ",
            "optionC": "  Madhav Rao-II ",
            "optionD": "  Baji Rao-II ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBaji Rao II (10 January, 1775 \u2013 28 January, 1851) was the last Peshwa of the Maratha Empire, and governed from 1795 to 1818. He was installed as a puppet ruler by the Maratha nobles, whose growing power prompted him to flee his capital Pune and sign the Treaty of Bassein (1802) with the British. The last Peshwa was Baji Rao-II. Duringhrs reign the peshwa ship was abolished by the British Government (Lord Harding-I, third Anglo Maratha battle). ",
            "keyString": "362151s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following had been the leader of a number of anti-British revolts in Sambalpur?",
            "optionA": "  Kattabomman ",
            "optionB": "  Surendra Sai ",
            "optionC": "  Utirat Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Sayyid Ahmad Barelvi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBy virtue of the Doctrine of Lapse, Lord Dalhousie annexed Sambalpur in 1849, as Narayan Singh had no male successor to succeed him. During the uprising of 1857 the sepoys set Surendra Sai and his brother Udyant Sai free. The resistance to British continued in Sambalpur under the leadership of Surendra Sai. ",
            "keyString": "362165s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On imprisonment in 1908 by the British, Bal Gangadhar Tilak was in",
            "optionA": "  Andaman and Nicobar ",
            "optionB": "  Rangoon ",
            "optionC": "  Singapore ",
            "optionD": "  Mandalay ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBal Gangadhar Tilak was imprisoned in 1908 to Mandalay for six years. Tilak criticise the Britishers in his newspaper, under a article name 'Bharat ki Durdasha' and this became the reason for his imprisonment.",
            "keyString": "403795s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Madras was returned by the French to the British in 1748 by the Treaty of",
            "optionA": "  Paris ",
            "optionB": "  Delhi ",
            "optionC": "  London ",
            "optionD": "  Aix-la-Chapelle ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMadras was returned by the French to the British in 1748 by the Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle. ",
            "keyString": "403830s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following counterpart of British in the Treaty of Salbai?",
            "optionA": "  The French ",
            "optionB": "  The Marathas ",
            "optionC": "  Tipu Sultan ",
            "optionD": "  The Nizam of Hyderabad ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Treaty of Salbai was signed on 17 May 1782, by representatives of the Maratha Empire and the British East India Company after long negotiations to settle the outcome of the First Anglo-Maratha War. David Anderson concluded the Treaty of Salbai on behalf of the East India Company. ",
            "keyString": "403847s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The master stroke of Lord Wellesley to establish British paramountcy in India was",
            "optionA": "  Doctrine of Lapse ",
            "optionB": "  Subsidiary Alliance ",
            "optionC": "  Mediatisation ",
            "optionD": "  Annexation of Indian States ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe master stroke of Lord Wellesley to establish British paramountcy in India was Subsidiary Alliance. ",
            "keyString": "403861s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In what way did the early nationalists undermine the moral foundations of the British rule with great success?",
            "optionA": "  By their agitation for Constitutional reforms ",
            "optionB": "  By advocating open revolt ",
            "optionC": "  By seeking foreign help against the British ",
            "optionD": "  By seeking the support of the Indians living abroad ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe very conditions of British rule helped the growth of national sentiment. Roy was the first Indian leader to start an agitation for political reforms in India. There is a moral evil which, if anything, is even greater. ",
            "keyString": "403874s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On account of severe British repression the Civil Disobedience movement was again suspended In July 1933 and people were asked to offer Satyagraha",
            "optionA": "  individually ",
            "optionB": "  in groups ",
            "optionC": "  locally ",
            "optionD": "  against liquor shops ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn account of severe British repression the Civil Disobedience movement was again suspended In July 1933 and people were asked to offer Satyagraha individually. ",
            "keyString": "442002s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was Lord Morley?",
            "optionA": "  Secretary of the state ",
            "optionB": "  Viceroy of India ",
            "optionC": "  Governor General of India ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Morley became secretary of state for India in Henry Campbell-Bannerman's Cabinet of 1905. ",
            "keyString": "442035s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Non-Cooperation Movement under Gandhi was in full swing during the Viceroyalty of",
            "optionA": "  Chelmsford ",
            "optionB": "  Irwin ",
            "optionC": "  Reading ",
            "optionD": "  Hardinge ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Non-Cooperation Movement under Gandhi was in full swing during the Viceroyalty of Reading. ",
            "keyString": "442051s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following charter act ended the monopoly of trade of east India Company with china and sea route also?",
            "optionA": "  Pitt's India Act, AD 1784 ",
            "optionB": "  The charter Act, 1813 AD ",
            "optionC": "  Charter Act, 1833 AD ",
            "optionD": "  The Regulating Act, AD 1773 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Charter act of 1813 ended the monopoly of the East India Company in India, however the company's monopoly in trade with china and trade in tea was remained intact. The charter act of 1813, for the first time explicitly defined the constitutional position of the British territories in India. ",
            "keyString": "442064s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Queen Victoria's famous proclamation, transferring authority from the East India Company to the Crown , was made from",
            "optionA": "  London ",
            "optionB": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionC": "  Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  Allahabad ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tQueen Victoria's famous proclamation, A Royal Durbar was held at Allahabad in November 1, 1858. A proclamation was issued by Queen Victoria. It was read at the Durbar by Lord Canning, who was the last Governor General and the first Viceroy of India. ",
            "keyString": "442076s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "An ambassador of the British King James I, who secured favourable privileges for the East India Company from Emperor Jahangir, was",
            "optionA": "  Hawkins ",
            "optionB": "  Henry Middleton ",
            "optionC": "  Thomas Roe ",
            "optionD": "  Josiah Child ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFrom 1615 to 1618, he was ambassador to the court at Agra, India, of the Great Mughal Ruler, Jahangir. The principal object of the mission was to obtain protection for the East India Company`s factory at Surat. At the Mughal court, Roe allegedly became a favorite of Jahangir and may have been his drinking partner. ",
            "keyString": "485941s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which region did Birsa Munda operate against the British?",
            "optionA": "  Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  Chhota Nagpur ",
            "optionC": "  Tarai ",
            "optionD": "  Manipur ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBirsa Munda was a great tribal leader belonging to the Munda Adivasi, the movement operate against Britishin Chhota Nagpur (Jharkhand) region. ",
            "keyString": "485973s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The single biggest item of British capital investment in India was",
            "optionA": "  Railways ",
            "optionB": "  Plantations and mines ",
            "optionC": "  Banking and insurance ",
            "optionD": "  Shipping ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe single biggest item of British capital investment in India was Railways. ",
            "keyString": "485987s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the Act made the governor of Bengal as Governor General of India?",
            "optionA": "  Pitt's India Act, 1784 ",
            "optionB": "  Charter Act, 1813 ",
            "optionC": "  Charter Act, 1833 ",
            "optionD": "  Regulating Act, 1773 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGovernor-General of Bengal was made Governor-General of India through the Charter Act of 1833. ",
            "keyString": "486000s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "British Crown assumed sovereignty over Indian from the East Indian Company in the year",
            "optionA": "  1857 ",
            "optionB": "  1858 ",
            "optionC": "  1859 ",
            "optionD": "  1860 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe government of India Act (1858) also known as the act for Good Government of India transferred the power to the British crown from East India company. ",
            "keyString": "486011s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the Viceroy at the time of Quit India Movement?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Mountbatten ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Wavell ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Linlithgow ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Irwin ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Linlithgow (1936 \u2013 1944) was the viceroy of India during Quit India Movement. The Quit India Movement (also known as the August Movement) was a civil disobedience movement launched by Mahatma Gandhi on August 8,1942 in Mumbai for complete independence ",
            "keyString": "527250s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sir Thomas Roe came to India with a letter from the British Monarch",
            "optionA": "  Queen Mary ",
            "optionB": "  Queen Elizabeth ",
            "optionC": "  James I ",
            "optionD": "  Queen Anne ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThis event also started the process of transforming the British East India Company from a group of merchants, to an organization with military force. In 1614, King James I of England sent a diplomat, Sir Thomas Roe, to visit the Mughal emperor, Jahangir, and negotiate a trade treaty. ",
            "keyString": "527283s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Subsidiary Alliance was introduced by __________",
            "optionA": "  Lord Wellesley ",
            "optionB": "  Sir John Shore ",
            "optionC": "  Robert Clive ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Subsidiary Alliance System was \"Non-Intervention Policy\" used by Lord Wellesley who was the Governor-General (1798-1805) to establish British Empire in India. According to this system, every ruler in India had to accept to pay a subsidy to the British for the maintenance of British army. ",
            "keyString": "527298s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The policy of Doctrine of lapse was introduced by __________",
            "optionA": "  Lord Wellesley ",
            "optionB": "  Lord William Bentinck ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Macaulay ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe doctrine of lapse was an annexation policy applied by the British East India Company in India until 1858. The policy is most commonly associated with Lord Dalhousie, who was the Governor General of the East India Company in India between 1848 and 1856. ",
            "keyString": "527310s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): On 25th April, 1809, the Treaty of Amritsar was signed between Ranjit Singh and East India Company.\nReason (R): Ranjit Singh wanted to increase the realm of his empire with the help of the company",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R is true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R is true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTreaty of Amritsar (1809) The Treaty of Amritsar of 1809 was an agreement between the British East India Company and Ranjit Singh, the Sikh leader who founded the Sikh empire. ",
            "keyString": "527321s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who put on the statute book two obnoxious measures the Vernacular press Act and the Indian Arms Act",
            "optionA": "  Lord Ripon ",
            "optionB": "  Lytton ",
            "optionC": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionD": "  Queen Victoria ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLytton put on the statute book two obnoxious measures\u2014 the vernacular press Act and Indian Arms Act. Lytton' s unpopular acts provoked a great storm of opposition in the country and led to the organisation of various political associations for carrying an anti-Government propaganda in the country. ",
            "keyString": "567666s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian Civil Service Act was passed during the Viceroyalty of",
            "optionA": "  Elgin ",
            "optionB": "  Canning ",
            "optionC": "  Minto ",
            "optionD": "  Lytton ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Canning (1858\u201362): The Indian Councils Act of 1862 was passed, which proved to be a landmark in the constitutional history of India. ",
            "keyString": "567702s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Ancient Monuments Preservation Act was passed during the viceroyalty of",
            "optionA": "  Ripon ",
            "optionB": "  Curzon ",
            "optionC": "  Hastings ",
            "optionD": "  Dalhousie ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOne of the most remarkable acts passed during the times of Lord Curzon was the Ancient Monuments Preservation Act of 1904. This act made any injury to the protected monuments an offence punishable under the law. ",
            "keyString": "567721s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When did the British Govt. start ruling India directly?",
            "optionA": "  After the Battle of Plassey ",
            "optionB": "  After the Battle of Panipat ",
            "optionC": "  After the war of Mysore ",
            "optionD": "  After Sepoy Mutiny ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter Sepoy Mutiny rule established in 1857, British govt. started ruling over India, Governor general became the Viceroy and Lord Canning became the last Governor General and first Viceroy. ",
            "keyString": "567737s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Diu was the colony of the __________",
            "optionA": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionB": "  English ",
            "optionC": "  Dutch ",
            "optionD": "  French ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDaman and Diu were once part of a combined union territory along with Goa (a Konkani-speaking region), before Goa became a state in 1987. The use of Portuguese, which was the territory's official language during the colonial period, is in decline and relegated to home use. ",
            "keyString": "567752s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to the terms of the treaty of Srirangapattanam, . . . . . . was ceded to the British",
            "optionA": "  Malabar ",
            "optionB": "  Cochi ",
            "optionC": "  Travancore ",
            "optionD": "  Mysore ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to the terms of the treaty of Srirangapattanam, Malabar was ceded to the British. ",
            "keyString": "610998s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Treaty between Ranjit Singh and the British was signed at",
            "optionA": "  Allahabad ",
            "optionB": "  Amritsar ",
            "optionC": "  Kashmir ",
            "optionD": "  Agra ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTreaty of Amritsar, (April 25, 1809), pact concluded between Charles T. Metcalfe, representing the British East India Company, and Ranjit Singh, head of the Sikh kingdom of Punjab. The British wanted a defensive treaty against the French and control of Punjab to the Sutlej River. ",
            "keyString": "611037s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When the East India Company came into existence, England was ruled by the__________",
            "optionA": "  Hanoverians ",
            "optionB": "  Stuarts ",
            "optionC": "  Normans ",
            "optionD": "  Tudors ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen the East India Company came into existence, England was ruled by the Stuarts. ",
            "keyString": "611055s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________ , the viceroy of India decided to partition Bengal for administrative purposes, creating a new province of East Bengal and Assam, with a population of 31 million people and with its capital at Dhaka",
            "optionA": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Rippon ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Hastings ",
            "optionD": "  Wellesley ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Curzon, the viceroy of India decided to partition Bengal for administrative purposes, creating a new province of East Bengal and Assam, with a population of 31 million people and with its capital at Dhaka.",
            "keyString": "611069s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Mutiny began in __________",
            "optionA": "  1557 ",
            "optionB": "  1657 ",
            "optionC": "  1857 ",
            "optionD": "  1957 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian Rebellion of 1857 is also called the Indian Mutiny, the Sepoy Mutiny, North India's First War of Independence or North India's first struggle for independence. It began on 10 May 1857 at Meerut, as a mutiny of sepoys of the British East India Company's army. ",
            "keyString": "611083s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Robert Clive, the Governor General of the __________",
            "optionA": "  Dutch ",
            "optionB": "  French ",
            "optionC": "  British ",
            "optionD": "  Portuguese ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMajor-General Robert Clive, 1st Baron Clive, KB, FRS, also known as Clive of India, Commander-in-Chief of British India, was a British officer and privateer who established the military and political supremacy of the East India Company in Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "656010s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Throughout the 19th century intermittent uprisings occurred in Malabar, especially in the __________ and Valluvanad taluks.Twenty two such riots were reported from different parts of Malabar",
            "optionA": "  Ernad ",
            "optionB": "  Cochi ",
            "optionC": "  Travancore ",
            "optionD": "  Kannur ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThroughout the 19th century intermittent uprisings occurred in Malabar, especially in the Ernad and Valluvanad taluks.Twenty two such riots were reported from different parts of Malabar. ",
            "keyString": "656043s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During their rule the British persuaded or forced cultivators in Bengal to grow__________",
            "optionA": "  Jute ",
            "optionB": "  Tea ",
            "optionC": "  Sugarcane ",
            "optionD": "  Wheat ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBritisher invested in agriculture to fulfil the demand of raw materials required for industries in Britain. So, British persuaded or forced cultivator in Bengal to grow Jute (it also known as golden fibre). ",
            "keyString": "656059s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What did the Rowlatt Act, 1919 empower the British government to do",
            "optionA": "  Foment class and caste strife ",
            "optionB": "  Shut down any industrial unit at will ",
            "optionC": "  Extend the period of imprisonment for Indians ",
            "optionD": "  Detain a person for any duration without a trial ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRowlatt Acts, (February 1919), legislation passed by the Imperial Legislative Council, the legislature of British India. The acts allowed certain political cases to be tried without juries and permitted internment of suspects without trial. ",
            "keyString": "656071s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1614 Sir Thomas Roe was instructed by __________ to visit the court of Jahangir, the Mughal emperor of India",
            "optionA": "  James I ",
            "optionB": "  Babur ",
            "optionC": "  Shajahan ",
            "optionD": "  Humayun ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1614 Sir Thomas Roe was instructed by James I to visit the court of Jahangir, the Moghul emperor of Hindustan to arrange a commercial treaty and to secure for the East India Company sites for commercial agencies. Sir Thomas was successful, and though the Great Moghul Jahangir was contemptuous of the presents sent him by James I, he sent him a remarkably polite letter. ",
            "keyString": "656084s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When were Morley-Minto reforms taken place?",
            "optionA": "  1905 ",
            "optionB": "  1909 ",
            "optionC": "  1919 ",
            "optionD": "  1857 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian Councils Act 1909, commonly known as the Morley-Minto Reforms (or as the Minto-Morley Reforms), was an Act of the Parliament of the United Kingdom that brought about a limited increase in the involvement of Indians in the governance of British India. ",
            "keyString": "700598s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The writers of the East India Company had their training in the college at __________ in England",
            "optionA": "  London ",
            "optionB": "  Manchester ",
            "optionC": "  Liverpool ",
            "optionD": "  Haileybury ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe writers of the East India Company had their training in the college at Haileybury in England. ",
            "keyString": "700637s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gandhiji's famous Quit India movement call to the British was given in",
            "optionA": "  1943 ",
            "optionB": "  1941 ",
            "optionC": "  1942 ",
            "optionD": "  1940 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhiji launched Quit India Movement on 8th August 1942 in Bombay session of congress. It is also known as August revolutoion. ",
            "keyString": "700655s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lord __________ is regarded to have been the father of local self-government in India",
            "optionA": "  Ripon ",
            "optionB": "  Bentinck ",
            "optionC": "  Curzon ",
            "optionD": "  Mayo ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Ripon is known as Father of Local Self Government in India. This was not enacted by any act, it was a resolution that was passed in 1882. ",
            "keyString": "700670s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which war lord is also known as 'little corporal'",
            "optionA": "  Alexander ",
            "optionB": "  Julius Caesar ",
            "optionC": "  Napoleon Bonaparte ",
            "optionD": "  Genghis Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNapoleon Bonaparte war lord is also known as 'little corporal'. ",
            "keyString": "700701s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among of the following was the Viceroy of India when Indian University Act, 1904 was passed?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Dufferin ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Lansdowne ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Minto ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the time period of Indian University act,1904 Lord Curzon was the Viceroy of India. ",
            "keyString": "742274s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When the Simon Commission visited India the Viceroy was",
            "optionA": "  Lloyd George ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Irwin ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Reading ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Ripon ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSimon Commission had visited India on April 3, 1926 Lord Irwin was appointed 30th Viceroy and Governor-General of India. In 1927, British government appointed a commission under the chairmanship of Sir John Simon. ",
            "keyString": "742308s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the Viceroy when the Jallianwala Bagh Massacre took place?",
            "optionA": "  Hardinge-II ",
            "optionB": "  Chelmsford ",
            "optionC": "  Reading ",
            "optionD": "  Irwin ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Chelmsford was the Viceroy of India when Jallianwala Bagh Massacre took place on 13 April 1919. ",
            "keyString": "742326s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Seringapatnam was the capital of __________",
            "optionA": "  Pazhassi Raja ",
            "optionB": "  Tipu Sultan ",
            "optionC": "  Kurumbranad Raja ",
            "optionD": "  Srimoolam Tirunal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1767 Maratha Peshwa Madhavrao defeated both Hyder Ali and Tipu Sultan and entered Srirangapatna, the capital of Mysore.",
            "keyString": "742341s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following on the chronology of appointment of Viceroys\nI. Reading\nII. Irwin\nIII. Wellingdon\nIV. Linlithgow",
            "optionA": "  I, II, III , IV ",
            "optionB": "  III, II, IV, II ",
            "optionC": "  IV, III, II, I ",
            "optionD": "  II, IV, III, I ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following on the chronology of appointment of Viceroys were Reading, Irwin, Wellingdon and Linlithgow. ",
            "keyString": "742355s45m54h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}